One day, Los Angeles Times columnist
أحد كتاب الأعمدة الصحفية في صحيفة لوس أنجليس
Steve Lopez was walking along
ستيف لوبيز كان يوماً يسير
the streets of downtown Los Angeles
في إحدى طرق وسط المدينة في لوس أنجليس
when he heard beautiful music.
عندما سمع موسيقى جميلة جداً
And the source was a man,
كانت تصدر من رجلٍ
an African-American man,
رجلٍ أمريكي من أصل أفريقي
charming, rugged, homeless,
ساحر .. مُعدم ... مُشرد
playing a violin that only had two strings.
يعزف على كمان يحوي فقط وترين
And I'm telling a story that many of you know,
وأنا أخبركم قصة يعرفها العديد منكم
because Steve's columns became the basis
لان أعمدة ستيف الصحفية كانت الأساس
for a book, which was turned into a movie,
لرواية .. تحولت فيما بعد لفلم
with Robert Downey Jr. acting as Steve Lopez,
قام بدور بطولته " روبرت جونيور " مؤدياً دور الصحفي ستيف لوبيز
and Jamie Foxx as Nathaniel Anthony Ayers,
و جيمي فوكس مؤدياً دور " ناثانيل أنتوني أريرز "
the Juilliard-trained double bassist
عازف القيثارة المتدرب في مدرسة جوليارد
whose promising career was cut short
والذي توقفت مسيرته الغنائية الواعدة
by a tragic affliction with paranoid schizophrenia.
بسبب التأثيرات المأساوية لحالة من رهاب إنفاصم الشخصية
Nathaniel dropped out of Juilliard, he suffered a complete breakdown,
وقد دفعت ناثانيل لترك جوليارد وعانى من إنهيار تام لاحقاً
and 30 years later he was living homeless
وبعد 30 عاماً أصبح بلا مأوى
on the streets of Skid Row in downtown Los Angeles.
بين أروقة شوارع منتصف مدينة لوس أنجليس في " سكيد رو "
I encourage all of you to read Steve's book or to watch the movie
وأنا أحثكم جميعاً على قراءة كتاب " ستيف " أو مشاهدة الفلم الذي صدر عنه
to understand not only the beautiful bond
لكي تستطيعوا أن تفهم الرابط الجميل
that formed between these two men,
الذي تشكل بين هذين الرجلين
but how music helped shape that bond,
وكيف ساعدت الموسيقى على تشكيل هذا الرابط
and ultimately was instrumental -- if you'll pardon the pun --
وقد لعبت دوراً فعالاً جداً .. حبذا لو عذرتموني في كلمات التعبير التالي
in helping Nathaniel get off the streets.
ولمساعدة ناثانيل للخروج من الشوارع
I met Mr. Ayers in 2008,
قابلت السيد ناثانيل في عام 2008
two years ago, at Walt Disney Concert Hall.
منذ عامين في قاعة تستضيف حفلاً لولت ديزني
He had just heard a performance of Beethoven's First and Fourth symphonies,
وكان قد أدى للتو معزوفة بتهوفن الأولى والرابعة
and came backstage and introduced himself.
ومن ثم وخلف الكواليس تعرف عليه
He was speaking in a very jovial and gregarious way
وقد كان يتحدث بروح مرحة وإجتماعية للغاية
about Yo-Yo Ma and Hillary Clinton
عن " يويو ما " وعن " هيلاري كلينتون "
and how the Dodgers were never going to make the World Series,
وكيف أن فريق " الدوجرز " لن يصل إلى بطولة العالم
all because of the treacherous first violin passage work
كُل هذا بسبب أن عازفي الكمان أجادوا المقطع الأول
in the last movement of Beethoven's Fourth Symphony.
من القسم الأخير من السيمفونية الرابعة لبيتهوفين
And we got talking about music, and I got an email from Steve a few days later
ومن ثم تحدثنا عن الموسيقى , وبعدة عدة أيام راسلت الصحفي ستيف
saying that Nathaniel was interested in a violin lesson with me.
أُخبره أن ناثانيل مهتم بدروس للعزف على الكمان معي
Now, I should mention that Nathaniel refuses treatment
ويجب أن أذكر لكم أن ناثانيل رفض العلاج
because when he was treated it was with shock therapy
لان العلاج في المصحة كان يتضمن علاجاً بالصدمات
and Thorazine and handcuffs,
وقيود أيدي و عقار " ثورازين "
and that scar has stayed with him for his entire life.
وبقي ذلك مؤثراً عليه ويرافقه طيلة حياته
But as a result now, he is prone to
ولكن اليوم ونتيجة لهذا فهو معرض
these schizophrenic episodes,
لتلك الحالات من الإنفصام
the worst of which can manifest themselves as
وأسوء ما قد يحدث نتيجة لهذا
him exploding
هو إنفجاره بصورة ما
and then disappearing for days,
ومن ثم إختفاءه لعدة أيام
wandering the streets of Skid Row,
متجولا في شوارع سكيد رو
exposed to its horrors, with the torment of his own mind
معرضاً نفسه للخطر .. في مواجهة عذابه الفكري الخاص
unleashed upon him.
والذي يخرج أمامه كل حين
And Nathaniel was in such a state of agitation
لقد كان ناثانيل في حالة من الإثارة
when we started our first lesson at Walt Disney Concert Hall --
عندما بدأنا درسنا الموسيقي الأول في قاعة حفلات ولت ديزني
he had a kind of manic glint in his eyes,
وقد كان يملك نظرة هوس براقة في عينيه
he was lost.
تشعرك أنه ضائع
And he was talking about
وكان يتحدث دوماً
invisible demons and smoke,
عن الشياطين والأدخنة الغير مرئية
and how someone was poisoning him in his sleep.
وكيف أن احدهم حاول تسميمه أثناء نومه
And I was afraid,
وكنت خائفاً
not for myself, but I was afraid
ليس على نفسي .. إنما
that I was going to lose him,
من إحتمال أن أخسره
that he was going to sink into one of his states,
جراء غرقه في إحدى حالاته التي كان يمر بها
and that I would ruin his relationship with the violin
وأنني سوف أُدمر علاقته مع الكمان
if I started talking about scales
إن بدأت التحدث عن المعطيات والجداول
and arpeggios and other exciting forms of
والأصوات التتابعية والاشكال الأخرى المثيرة
didactic violin pedagogy.
لعلم التربية بواسطة الكمان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, I just started playing.
لذا بدأت بالعزف على الفور
And I played the first movement of the Beethoven Violin Concerto.
وعزفت القسم الأول من مقطوعة بيتهوفين بواسطة الكمان
And as I played,
وأنا أعزف
I understood that there was a profound change
أستطعت أن أعيَّ تغيراً
occurring in Nathaniel's eyes.
يحدث في عينيّ ناثانيل
It was as if he was in the grip of some invisible pharmaceutical,
كان الأمر كما لو أنه حصل على جرعة خفية من الأدوية
a chemical reaction, for which my playing the music
مما أنتج ردة فعل كيميائية تجاه الموسيقى التي أعزف
was its catalyst.
والتي كانت المُحفز لردة الفعل تلك
And Nathaniel's manic rage
وتحول هوس ناثانيل بالغضب
was transformed into understanding,
إلى نوع من الفهم والوعي
a quiet curiosity and grace.
مع قليل من الفضول والراحة
And in a miracle, he lifted his own violin
وكمعجزة .. رفع آلة الكمان الخاصة به
and he started playing, by ear,
وبدأ يعزف تبعاُ لسمعه
certain snippets of violin concertos
بعض مقاطع من حفلة الكمان
which he then asked me to complete -- Mendelssohn,
ومن ثم طلب مني أن أكمل العزف ,, أن أعزف " مينديلسون "
Tchaikovsky, Sibelius.
تشايكوفيسكي , سيبيلوس
And we started talking about music, from Bach
ومن ثم تحدثنا عن الموسيقى وتحدثنا عن " باخ "
to Beethoven and Brahms,
و " بيتهوفين " و " برهامز "
Bruckner, all the B's,
" برنكنير " وكل العازفين الذي يبدأ أسمهم بحرف الباء
from Bartók, all the way up to Esa-Pekka Salonen.
من " بارتوك , وصولاً إلى " عيسى بيكا سالونين "
And I understood that he not only
وقد أدركت حينها ليس فقط
had an encyclopedic knowledge of music,
أنه موسوعة معلومات موسيقية
but he related to this music at a personal level.
إنما أنه أيضاً مرتبط إلى كل تلك الموسيقى بصورة شخصية ومباشرة
He spoke about it with the kind of passion
وقد تحدث عنها بشغف ..
and understanding that I share with my colleagues
ووعي وفهم كما أتحدث أنا مع زملائي
in the Los Angeles Philharmonic.
في جمعية محبي الموسيقى في لوس أنجليس
And through playing music and talking about music,
وعبر العزف والتحدث عن الموسيقى
this man had transformed
تغير الرجل
from the paranoid, disturbed man
من رجل مصاب بالرهاب رجلٍ مضطرب
that had just come from walking the streets
والذي كان يجول شوارع
of downtown Los Angeles
وسط مدينة لوس أنجليس
to the charming, erudite,
إلى رجل ساحر , ضليع المعرفة
brilliant, Juilliard-trained musician.
ذكي , موسيقي متدرب في جوليارد
Music is medicine. Music changes us.
إن الموسيقى دواء . إن الموسيقى تغيرنا
And for Nathaniel, music is sanity.
وبالنسبة لناثانيل كانت الموسيقى هي الصحة العقلية
Because music allows him to take his thoughts
لان الموسيقى كانت تسمح له بتحويل أفكاره
and delusions and shape them
وأوهامه وتشذيبها
through his imagination and his creativity,
عبر خياله وإبداعه
into reality.
إلى الواقعية
And that is an escape
وكان هذا هو مهربه من
from his tormented state.
حالته الهوسية التي كانت تعذب نفسه
And I understood that this was the very essence of art.
وقد إستوعبت أن هذا هو دور الفن حقاً وجوهره
This was the very reason why we made music,
وهذا هو السبب الحقيقي الذي يجعلنا نصنع الموسيقى
that we take something that exists within all of us
وبإستيعاب هذا الشيء الذي يحيط بنا دائما
at our very fundamental core,
في منتصف نواة عواطفنا ..
our emotions,
الأساسية
and through our artistic lens,
وعبر كل مناظرينا الفنية
through our creativity, we're able to shape those emotions into reality.
وعبر إبداعنا , فنحن قادرون على أن نشذب ونحول تلك العواطف إلى حقيقة
And the reality of that expression
و واقعية ذلك التعبير عن المشاعر
reaches all of us
سيصل إلى الجميع حتماً
and moves us, inspires and unites us.
ويحركهم .. ويُلهمهم ويوحدهم
And for Nathaniel,
وبالنسبة لناثانيل
music brought him back into a fold of friends.
فقد أعادته الموسيقى إلى أصدقائه الكثر
The redemptive power of music brought him back
وقد أعادته قوتها - الموسيقى - المسيطرة
into a family of musicians
إلى عائلة الموسيقين
that understood him,
الذين يفهمونه
that recognized his talents
ويقدرون موهبته
and respected him.
ويحترمونه
And I will always make music with Nathaniel,
وسوف أعزف دوما الموسيقى مع ناثانيل
whether we're at Walt Disney Concert Hall
سواء كنا في حفل لولت ديزني
or on Skid Row, because he reminds me
أو كنا في شوارع "سكيد رو " لأنه يذكرني
why I became a musician.
بالسبب الذي جعل مني موسيقياً
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Thank you. Thanks.
برونو جيساني : شكراً . شكراً
Robert Gupta.
روبرت جوبتا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Robert Gupta: I'm going to play something that I shamelessly stole from cellists.
روبرت جوبتا : أريد أن أعزف شيئأ للأسف سرقته من عازف كمان
So, please forgive me.
لذا إعذروني .. من فضلكم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)